A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Correspondence with United States Senators and Representatives FA1411
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Correspondence with United States Senators and Representatives
1969 April-1986 May
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA1411
1.9 Cubic Feet 5 document containers
Scope and Contents
The collection includes correspondence related to pending grant proposals, requests for testimony before Congress, internal Foundation memos, clippings of the Congressional Record related to Foundation issues, and acknowledgments of receipt of Ford Foundation publications.
Further information regarding the subject of the correspondence can be found in an individual folder's additional description note.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas.
During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was transferred to RAC in 2017 by the Ford Foundation and ingested by RAC as Accession 2017:085.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series:
1. Correspondence with U.S. Senators
2. Correspondence with U.S. Representatives
Ford Foundation; United States. Congress. House; United States. Congress. Senate -- History -- 20th century
- Correspondence with U.S. Senators, 1970-1985; 1
  Scope and Contents
  Arranged alphabetically by Senator's last name
  - Abourezk, James - South Dakota, 1976 April-May (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Rural America
  - Aiken, George D. - Vermont, 1972 May-1974 July (Box 1, Folder 2)
    University of Vermont
  - Allen, James B. - Alabama, 1977 August (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Birmingham Festival of Arts
  - Allot, Gordon - Colorado, 1970 October-1972 May (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Anderson, Clinton P. - New Mexico, 1970 June-1972 May (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Biographical study of Clinton P. Anderson, 1969 Tax Reform Act
  - Baker, Howard - Tennessee, 1973 May-1977 March (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Congressional Record - MITRE Report, Quality of Work Program, American Enterprise Institute for Public Policy Research, National Academy of Public Administration, Vanderbilt University News Archive
  - Bayh, Birch - Indiana, 1970 March-1977 September (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Drug Issues and Children's Issues (Senate Subcommittee on Juvenile Delinquency), CATALYST ONE, Rehabilitation Services Vital to Prisoners (RSVP)
  - Beall, J. Glenn, Jr. - Maryland, 1971 August-1976 April (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Tax Analysts and Advocates, St. Joseph College
  - Bellmon, Henry - Oklahoma, 1974 June (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Personal charitable request
  - Bennett, Wallace F. - Utah, 1970 June-1973 February (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Environmental Resources Recycling Foundation
  - Bible, Alan - Nevada, 1972 November (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Alaska Native Foundation
  - Brock, Bill - Tennessee, 1974 October-1975 June (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Quality of Work Program, American Enterprise Institute
  - Brooke, Edward W. - Massachusetts, 1972 March-1978 April (Box 1, Folder 13)
    The Bicentennial Council of the Thirteen Original States Fund, Inc., Circle, Inc., Joint Center for Political Studies
  - Buckley, James - New York, 1974 June-1976 January (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Grants relating to abortion
  - Byrd, Harry - Virginia, 1974 July-1980 May (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Washington Center for Metropolitan Studies, acknowledgment of publications sent to office
  - Case, Clifford P. - New Jersey, 1972 March-1977 September (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Church, Frank - Idaho, 1970 September-1980 April (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Population Research Seminar, nuclear proliferation, Alaska Native Foundation, Resources for the Future - fisheries aspect of the third United Nations conference on the Law of the Sea, Congressional Record November 30, 1970
  - Clark, Dick - Iowa, 1975 February-1977 March (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Food for Peace Program, "New Opportunities for Tax Exempts: A Conference on Lobbying," Rural America, Members of Congress for Peace through Law, US-Japan Parliamentary Exchange Program
  - Cook, Marlow W. - Kentucky, 1971 March-1972 August (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Centre College and Pikeville College for the Venture Fund grant program
  - Cooper, John Sherman - Kentucky, 1970 August-1972 October (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Pikeville College
  - Curtis, Carl T. - Nebraska, 1971 February-1975 May (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Dodd, Thomas J. - Connecticut, 1970 December (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Arranging Senator Dodd's papers
  - Dominick, Peter H. - Colorado, 1970 September-1974 June (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Koshare Indian Museum, Tax on Private Foundations
  - Eagleton, Thomas - Missouri, 1973 August 10-1983 December 8 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Senate Subcommittee on Education, Arts, and Humanities
  - Eastland, James O. - Mississippi, 1972 June (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Criticism of grants to Puerto Rico
  - Edwards, Elaine S. - Louisiana, 1972 August (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Louisiana State University - Venture Fund
  - Ervin, Sam - North Carolina, 1973 October 26-1974 February 4 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    First Amendment issues, National Academy of Public Administration Foundation - Senate Select Committee on Presidential Campaign Activities
  - Everett, Jordan B. - North Carolina, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Appalachian State University - Venture Fund
  - Fannin, Paul - Arizona, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Arizona Job Colleges
  - Fong, Hiram L. - Hawaii, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Hawaii Environmental Simulation Laboratory (HESL) and US Senate Staff Club
  - Fulbright, F. W. - Arkansas, 1970 September-1976 January (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Board of Foreign Scholarships, Committee on Foreign Relations, Texarkana Special Education Center, United Nations Conference on the Law of the Sea
  - Goldwater, Barry M. - Arizona, 1971 March-1985 August (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Tucson Dome Site, Southwest Institute for Research on Women, Arizona Job Colleges, Navajo Community College, Community Television of Southern California, Brookings Institution
  - Goodell, Charles E. - New York, 1970 May (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Congressional Record
  - Gravel, Michael - Alaska, 1970 July-1979 June (Box 1, Folder 34)
    General Stock Ownership Plan, Meeting on Financed Capitalism, Enep'ut Center in Fairbanks, American Indian Press Association, Graduate Fellowships for Native Americans, Center for Northern Education at the University of Alaska, leadership development among Alaskan native groups
  - Griffin, Robert - Michigan, 1974 May-1975 September (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Gurney, Edward J. - Florida, 1972 November (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Hansen, Clifford P. - Wyoming, 1972 June-1977 May (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Metric system in schools, Political Science Chair at Mississippi State University, Energy Policy Project
  - Harris, Fred R. - Oklahoma, 1970 December-1971 February (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Hart, Gary - Colorado, 1979 April-1985 June (Box 1, Folder 39)
    National Service, Chicano Education Project, Southwest Institute for Research on Women and Women's Studies Program at the University of Northern Colorado, conference on "Transitions in Industrial Democracies"
  - Hart, Philip A. - Michigan, 1970 June-1971 June (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Manistee Music Camp, Auto Repair Minority Enterprise Feasibility Study Funding Request
  - Hartke, Vance - Indiana, 1971 November-1976 April (Box 2, Folder 41)
    Correspondence related to Senator Hartke's role as Chairman of the Subcommittee on Foundations, 4% excise tax on Foundations, 1969 Tax Act
  - Haskell, Floyd K. - Colorado, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Hathaway, William D. - Maine, 1974 January-1977 September (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Hayakawa, S. I. - California, 1977 September-1980 May (Box 2, Folder 44)
    Community colleges, community development, and San Francisco Consortium
  - Hecht, Chic - Nevada, 1985 September (Box 2, Folder 45)
    "A LULAC School Success/College Preparatory Research Project"
  - Huddleston, Walter D. - Kentucky, 1974 January-1977 March 22 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Hughes, Harold E. - Iowa, 1971 July-1974 February (Box 2, Folder 47)
    Chile Implications for US Foreign Policy, International Programs Subcommittee of the Labor and Public Welfare Committee of the Senate
  - Humphrey, Hubert H. - Minnesota, 1971 July-1977 September (Box 2, Folder 48)
    Humphrey Institute, Food for Peace Program, Tax Analysts and Advocates, Courage Center of Minnesota Society for Crippled Children and Adults, black educators, Senate Foreign Agricultural Policy Subcommittee, the Common Market - Norway, Metropolitan Transit Commission, Concordia College - Venture Funds
  - Jackson, Henry M. - Washington, 1971 September-1981 May (Box 2, Folder 49)
    Documentary about a tour of Eastern Europe by the Radost Folk Ensemble, Energy Supply Act and Synthetic Fuels Production Act, Manpower Demonstration Research Corporation, State of Washington Department of Social and Health Services, Senate Interior and Insular Affairs Committee - National Fuels and Energy Policy
  - Javits, Jacob K. - New York, 1970 April-1979 May (Box 2, Folder 50)
    New York State Alliance to Save Energy, Pacific News Service and the Third Century America Project at the University of California, Boro Park, Japan-US Parliamentary Exchange, Reproduction and Human Welfare, Chinese Development Council, Community Law Offices, Committee of Nine, Nassau County's Productivity Study, Arab-Western Dialogue, Gateway National Recreation Area Advisory Committee, New York conservation commissions, Carnegie Endowment for International Peace for the benefit of the Middle East Commission, Puerto Rican Legal Defense Fund, South Bronx housing, Howard University Metropolitan Research Center, East Harlem Extension Service, New York City housing, Near East Emergency Donation fund, Urban Skills Inc., New York City fund, Minority Enterprise Small Business Investment Company, Chinese Youth Council for a Chinatown Language Center, Local Development Corporation, Anfoushy Fisheries Training Center - UAR, Pratt Center for Community Improvement, Harlem Preparatory School
  - Kassebaum, Nancy Landon - Kansas, 1985 November (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Lieberman, Joseph I. - Connecticut, 1972 December (Box 2, Folder 52)
    National Black Veterans Fraternity
  - Long, Russell - Louisiana, 1970 September-1979 June (Box 2, Folder 53)
    Energy Policy Project, Congressional Quarterly
  - Magnuson, Warren G. - Washington, 1970 September-1978 March (Box 2, Folder 54)
    Office of Environmental Mediation, Oak Tree Association, Law of the Sea, Energy Policy Project, the Committee for International Environmental Programs (IEPC) and Special Committee on the Problems of the Environment (SCOPE)
  - Mansfield, Mike - Montana, 1972 February-1974 April (Box 2, Folder 55)
    Congressional Interest in US Dependency on Imports of Foreign Raw Materials, Environmental Quality Council of the State of Montana, Urban Affairs Institute, "Youth to the Country Inc."
  - Mathias, Charles McC., Jr. - Maryland, 1971 August-1985 September (Box 2, Folder 56)
    Basic health research, European experience with juvenile delinquency, Mount Saint Joseph College
  - McClellan, John - Arkansas, 1973 July (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - McGee, Gale W. - Wyoming, 1972 February-1975 October (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - McGovern, George - South Dakota, 1970 September-1976 May (Box 2, Folder 59)
    Rural America, street-light restoration in Deadwood, South Dakota, Conference on National Food and Nutrition Policy, MLK Jr. Memorial Scholarship Foundation at the University of South Dakota, Oglala Sioux Radio Communications program
  - McIntyre, Thomas J. - New Hampshire, 1973 March-1977 March (Box 2, Folder 60)
    New Hampshire conservation commissions
  - Metcalf, Lee - Montana, 1972 October-1977 August (Box 2, Folder 61)
    Questionnaire for Foundations, Rural America, Native American Rights Fund, Joint Committee hearings on Congress and Mass Communications, Urban Affairs Institute, Fishery Studies
  - Mondale, Walter F. - Minnesota, 1971 March-1976 July (Box 2, Folder 62)
    Reducing payout rates for foundations and reduction in excise taxes, Institute for Educational Leadership, Subcommittee on Children and Youth, Minneapolis College of Art and Design, juvenile justice system, women's education projects, Equal Educational Opportunity, Educational Testing Service, Emergency School Aid Act and the Quality Integrated Education Act, Alaska Native Foundation
  - Montoya, Joseph M. - New Mexico, 1970 April-1973 October (Box 2, Folder 63)
    Interstate Research Associates - Centro de Desarrollo Communal, Learning about Learning Educational Foundation, Central Clearing House, Southwest Valley Youth Development Project, Junior Olympic Indian Sports and Recreational Program, Mexican-American Legal Defense and Educational Fund, medical satellite clinic - Pajarito, Albuquerque, Lourdes Halfway House, Centro de Estudios Chicanos at San Diego State College
  - Morgan, Robert - North Carolina, 1975 September (Box 2, Folder 64)
    Angry letter regarding Foundation sent to Senator Morgan from constituent
  - Moss, Frank E. - Utah, 1973 July-1975 November (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Mundt, Karl E. - South Dakota, 1970 May (Box 2, Folder 66)
    1970 and 1971 seminars for advanced civil servants from NATO countries
  - Murphy, George - California, 1970 December (Box 2, Folder 67)
    Request for grant for Murphy's staff to assist with transitioning from public to private life
  - Murray, Martin L. - Pennsylvania State Senator, 1973 February (Box 2, Folder 68)
    Requesting Comprehensive School Improvement Program survey
  - Muskie, Edmund S. - Maine, 1970 April-1977 February (Box 2, Folder 69)
    New England Energy Policy Council, Indirect Aid to the Arts, Clean Air Act, Skowhegan School, Maine conservation commissions, Ford Foundation and the environment, National Urban Fellows Program, Intergovernmental Personnel Act, Domaine School for Orchestral Training
  - Nelson, Gaylord - Wisconsin, 1970 June-1978 February (Box 2, Folder 70)
    Comprehensive Employment and Training Act (CETA), Quality Education Act, pesticide control
  - Pastore, John O. - Rhode Island, 1971 January-1974 November (Box 3, Folder 71)
    Rhode Island School of Design, Rhode Island Group Health Association, Chemke Mercy Hospital in Nigeria
  - Pearson, James B. - Kansas, 1974 October (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Percy, Charles H. - Illinois, 1970 January-1984 May (Box 3, Folder 73)
    "Women in Development: Looking to the Future," Fermilab, population and economic development, Alliance to Save Energy, urban affairs, national work demonstration project, 1969 Tax Reform Act, Energy Policy Project, School of the Art Institute and the University of Illinois, Council on Responsible Driving, Community Renewal Society
  - Prouty, Winston - Vermont, 1971 May (Box 3, Folder 74)
    Pay As You Earn (PAYE)
  - Randolph, Jennings - West Virginia, 1972 May-1977 September (Box 3, Folder 75)
    Human Resource Development Foundation, West Virginia Heritage Series, Alderson-Broaddus College
  - Ribicoff, Abraham - Connecticut, 1970 June-1979 January (Box 3, Folder 76)
    University of Hartford, creating Department of Education, work demonstration project, environmental regulation, Yale University scholarships to studio arts and fellowships for professional artists, Connecticut Housing and Investment Fund, "Triage" program - Connecticut Council on Human Services, Greater Hartford Process Inc. and Midstate Regional Planning Agency of Connecticut, creating cabinet-level Departments of Community Development and Human Resources
  - Russell, Richard B. - Georgia, 1972 January-February (Box 3, Folder 77)
    Richard B. Russell Library
  - Saxbe, William B. - Ohio, 1970 May-June (Box 3, Folder 78)
    Liberation Institute of Ohio
  - Schweiker, Richard S. - Pennsylvania, 1970 November-1977 September (Box 3, Folder 79)
    Lincoln University
  - Scott, Hugh - Pennsylvania, 1973 April-1976 June (Box 3, Folder 80)
    National supported work demonstration project, Telmen, Chatham College, College Misericordia, University of Pennsylvania, and Swarthmore College, Joint Center for Political Studies, Institute for Court Management - Court Executive Development Program
  - Smith, Margaret Chase - Maine, 1970 March-October (Box 3, Folder 81)
    Machias River Watershed - Eastern Maine Development District, Pierre Monteux Memorial Foundation
  - Sparkman, John J. - Alabama, 1978 September (Box 3, Folder 82)
    US-Soviet relations - "Effective Support for Human Rights," S. 2420 International Development Cooperation Act of 1978, Birmingham Festival of Arts, Southern Development Foundation, US multinational corporations and their impact on Atlantic relations, Neighborhood Housing Services, Alabama Public Schools, tenant affairs program in St. Louis, Southeast Alabama Self-Help Association, Florida Memorial Hospital, Resources for the Future and the National Planning Association
  - Stevenson, Adlai, III - Illinois, 1973 January-1975 June (Box 3, Folder 83)
    Washington Center for Metropolitan Studies, Ascending Citizens Development Corporation - industrial park in East St. Louis
  - Stone, Richard (Dick) - Florida, 1977 April (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Symington, Stuart - Missouri, 1970 September-1975 September (Box 3, Folder 85)
    Avila College - David E. Bell speaking in President Truman series, Block Partnership Program
  - Taft, Robert - Ohio, 1974 January-1975 September (Box 3, Folder 86)
    Columbus College of Art and Design
  - Talmadge, Herman - Georgia, 1970 June-1980 July (Box 3, Folder 87)
    Savannah Landmark Rehabilitation Project, Atlanta Urban League, Atlanta College of Art and the University of Georgia scholarships, Interdenominational Theological Center in Atlanta, National Shakespeare Company - summer festival, Atlanta University Center Corporation
  - Thompson, Frank, Jr. - New Jersey, 1970 May-1971 May (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - Tower, John - Texas, 1973 April-1975 November (Box 3, Folder 89)
    La Raza, Texas Southern University, Fort Stockton Chamber of Commerce - industrial park
  - Tunney, John V. - California, 1971 July-1976 February (Box 3, Folder 90)
    San Francisco Public Schools, National Conference on Education for Law and Justice, public interest law, Interstate Research Associates - Centro de Desarollo Communal, Public Education Program - East Los Angeles, Charles H. Sawyer's research - University of California at Los Angeles, Urban Affairs Institute in Los Angeles, Chicano radio proposal
  - Tydings, Joseph D. - Maryland, 1970 March-1976 June (Box 3, Folder 91)
    Aviation Consumer Action Project, Historic Anapolis renovation
  - Tsongas, Paul - Massachusetts, 1979 May-1982 June (Box 3, Folder 92)
    Lowell Development and Financial Corporation (LDFC)
  - Vaughn, Jackie III - Michigan State Senator, 1985 August (Box 3, Folder 93)
    Seeking funding for independent research study and thesis on the folklore of the Upcountry Region of South Carolina
  - Williams, Harrison A., Jr. - New Jersey, 1970 September-1979 May (Box 3, Folder 94)
    Working Class Women in Hoboken - Stevens Institute of Technology, House of Insight Rehabilitation Center in Newark, Tucson conference on school finance, national supported work demonstration project, occupational health, Save Lucy (the Elephant), "The Work Ethic"
  - Yarborough, Ralph W. - Texas, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 95)
  - Young, Milton - North Dakota, 1971 March-1975 September (Box 3, Folder 96)
    Concordia College Venture Fund, Catholic Indian Mission - Standing Rock Reservation playground equipment
- Correspondence with U.S. Representatives, 1969-1986; 2
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by Representative's last name
  - Abdnor, James - South Dakota, 1976 April-August (Box 3, Folder 97)
    Promotional campaign for United Sioux Indian Tribes of South Dakota during the US bicentennial
  - Abzug, Bella S. - New York, 1973 March-1976 May (Box 3, Folder 98)
    Woodrow Wilson fellowship dissertation winners in the area of women's studies, Washington Heights Educational Film Workshop, The 51st State News Program
  - Addabbo, Joseph P. - New York, 1984 May-July (Box 3, Folder 99)
    Far Rockaway YM-YWHA
  - Albert, Carl - Oklahoma, 1970 September-1975 September (Box 3, Folder 100)
    Alaska Native Foundation, Oklahoma Indian Rights Association, housing design
  - Anderson, John - Illinois, 1972 April-1974 March (Box 3, Folder 101)
    Center for Law in the Public Interest, HR 7285 - tax reform and foundations
  - Andrews, Ike - North Carolina, 1974 August (Box 3, Folder 102)
    North Carolina Manpower Development Corporation
  - Ashbrook, John M. - Ohio, 1977 May (Box 3, Folder 103)
  - Ashley, Thomas Ludlow - Ohio, 1972 August-1974 December (Box 3, Folder 104)
    Urban growth study tours, Carlos C. Campbell book project
  - Aspinall, Wayne N. - Colorado, 1972 May (Box 3, Folder 105)
  - Badillo, Herman - New York, 1972 January-1976 June (Box 3, Folder 106)
    DUME Spanish Theatre, Legal Action Center of the City of New York, Universidad Boricua, Puerto Rican Legal Defense and Education Fund, The 51st State, bilingual counselors for service in both New York and Puerto Rico, prison reform, East Harlem Environmental Extension Service, Inc.
  - Bauman, Robert E. - Maryland, 1974 April (Box 3, Folder 107)
  - Beard, Robin - Tennessee, 1975 May-1979 April (Box 3, Folder 108)
    All-Volunteer Force, Youth and the Needs of the Nation, problems in the military, Quality of Work Program
  - Bedell, Berkley - Iowa, 1986 May (Box 3, Folder 109)
    Home Group, Inc. fitness trail in Paullina, Iowa
  - Begich, Nick - Alaska, 1972 October (Box 3, Folder 110)
  - Bell, Alphonzo - California, 1973 February (Box 3, Folder 111)
    Open Space, Inc. - innovative and alternative educational programs
  - Benitez, Jaime - Puerto Rico, 1973 June-1975 January (Box 3, Folder 112)
    Graduate Fellowship Program for Puerto Ricans
  - Biester, Edward G. - Pennsylvania, 1973 July (Box 3, Folder 113)
  - Bingham, Jonathan B. - New York, 1974 September-1980 February (Box 3, Folder 114)
    Population assistance programs, mutual housing association, Legal Action Center
  - Blackburn, Ben - Georgia, 1974 March (Box 3, Folder 115)
  - Bolling, Richard - Missouri, 1970 October-1974 January (Box 3, Folder 116)
    Harry S. Truman Lecture Series at Avila College
  - Bowen, David - Mississippi, 1973 April (Box 3, Folder 117)
    Mississippi Economic Development Corporation
  - Brademas, John - Indiana, 1969 September-1975 December (Box 4, Folder 118)